If you want to know something about yourself, sit on your bed one night and say,
如果你想了解自己的一些事情 那就在某个晚上 坐在你自己的床上 跟自己说
what's one thing I'm doing wrong, that I know I'm doing wrong, that I could fix, that I would fix.
我正在做错的那件事是什么 我知道我在做错什么 我能改正 我想改正
You meditate on that, you'll get an answer.
你对此进行沉思 你会得到一个答案
And it won't be one you want, but it'll be the necessary one.
这个答案可能不是你想要的那个 但它是必要的那个
When you're trapped, some of it's your own inadequacy.
当你陷入困境 一部分原因是因为你自己的不足
What you can do to begin with is every bloody thing you possibly can do to put yourself in the most virtuous and powerful negotiating position possible.
首先你能做的是尽你所能做的一切 让自己处于最有德性（最有利）和最有力的谈判位置
Wherever I go in the world, people come up to me and they often have a pretty rough story to relate.
无论我走到世界哪里 人们都会向我走来 他们经常有一些相当艰难的故事要讲
It's an awful thing because you see, even in the revelation of their triumph, the initial depth of their despair.
这是一件可怕的事情 因为即使在他们胜利的喜悦中 你也能看到他们最初的绝望之深
So I wouldn't change that.
所以我无法改变那一点
But it's not nothing.
但这并非无关紧要（虚无）
它肯定不仅仅是幸福
It's certainly not just happiness.
It's better than happiness. But it's almost unbearable.
它比幸福更好 但它几乎难以承受
Quick one.
Can you do me a favour if you're listening to this and hit the subscribe button, the the follow button wherever you're listening to this podcast.
如果你在听这个并且点击了订阅按钮 无论你在哪里听这个播客 非常感谢你
Thank you so much.
（这是）你们一直在等待的对话
The conversation you guys have been waiting for.
我这么说是因为自从我宣布乔丹·彼得森来到这里
I say that because of the thousands and thousands of messages I've had since I announced that Jordan Peterson, the man himself,
这个人从加拿大远道而来 坐在我的“厨房”里与我交谈 我收到了成千上万的消息
all the way from Canada came here to sit in my kitchen and have a conversation with me.
And what a conversation it was.
这真是一次了不起的对话
One of the most moving moments in the history of this podcast takes place in this conversation.
这个播客历史上最感人的时刻之一就发生在这次对话中
And I think the thing that people love about Jordan Peterson is his unrelenting desire to just say what he believes to be true,
我认为人们喜欢乔丹·彼得森的原因是他毫不动摇的只说出他认为是真实的东西 不是他认为是正确的东西
not what he believes to be correct,
不是人们想听的东西
not what people want to hear,
不是人们乐于听到的东西
not what people will be happy to hear.
And it's because of that,
正因为如此 正因为他追求真理 他已经改变了数以百万计的人的生活
it's because of his pursuit of truth that he's managed to change millions and millions and millions of people's lives.
这绝对不是夸张
That is absolutely no understatement.
所以不用再说了 我是斯蒂芬·巴特利特 这是《CEO日记》
So without further ado, I'm Stephen Bartlett, and this is the diary of a CEO.
我希望没人在听
I hope nobody's listening, but if you are, then please keep this to yourself.
但如果你在听的话 请保守这个秘密
首先 我觉得我应该感激你，我想说谢谢你对我的生活产生的影响
First, I feel like I owe you a debt of gratitude and I want to say thank you for the impact you've had on my life and I'll point at the specific impact you've had on my life.
我会指出你对我的生活产生的具体影响
And you asked me before we started recording why this podcast had been successful.
录音开始前你问我为什么这个播客会成功
其中一个原因实际上是我从读你的书和听你的讲话中获得的 那就是这种真正的承诺 努力做真实的自己 努力表达真实
One of the reasons is actually something I've gained from reading and listening to your work and that's this real commitment to trying to be your true self and trying to be your truth.
如果我不了解真理在生活和人际关系的各个方面的重要性 这个播客就不会成功 我也不会在追求自我方面成功 这对我来说是非常关键的一点
This podcast wouldn't be successful and I wouldn't have been successful in terms of
pursuing myself had I not understood the importance of truth across all facets of life and in my relationships, which is a real pivotal thing for me.
这要感谢你的工作
And that's thanks to you.
So what's changed in your relationships as a consequence of that?
那么 因此你的关系发生了什么变化？
所以我相信 如果你不说真话 不表达真实的自己 真正与某人建立联系是非常困难的
So I believe it's really difficult to truly connect with someone if you're not speaking and being your truth.
And I wasn't, I think I was wearing a mask in my relationships in the context if I didn't express how I was thinking and feeling,
而我 我没有做到 我认为如果我不表达我的想法和感受 我在人际关系中就戴着面具 我试图成为我认为我的伴侣希望我成为的人
I was trying to be who I thought my partner wanted me to be.
而当我放下面具 开始说出我的真实想法时
And at the point when I like, I let down the mask and I started speaking my truth,
Actually, as I was departing from the relationship, the relationship got stronger than ever before.
实际上 当我正要离开这段关系时 这段关系比以往任何时候都更加坚强 就像我们从未真正建立过联系 直到我对她 对我的感受 对我想要的生活保持真实
And it was like we were never actually connected until I was being true with her, with my feelings, with what I wanted, with my life.
从那以后 我会说我的关系是我所见过的所有浪漫关系中 最坚强的一个
And since then, I would categorize my relationship as being the strongest thing I've ever seen in terms of a romantic connection with someone.
And so when you were starting to talk in your relationship in a more truthful manner, what did that mean that you had to admit?
这意味着你必须承认什么？我是说你刚才说的部分是你试图成为的人和你真正的自我之间的脱节 这是一个人格问题 对吗？
I mean, you just said that part of it was a disconnect between who you were trying to be and who you really were.
So that's a persona issue, right?
So you think maybe, and everyone has this proclivity to some degree, is they're deeply self-conscious
所以你可能认为 每个人在某种程度上都有这种倾向 那就是他们非常关注自我并深陷不确定性
and uncertain, and so instead of allowing the person they're with to connect with that underlying uncertainty and inadequacy, they act out a persona.
因此 他们不会让身边的人感受到潜在的不确定性和不足 他们表现出一种人格
然后问题是 也许对方爱上了那个人格 但那里没有真正的联系
And then the problem is is that, well, perhaps the person falls in love with that persona, but there's no real connection there, it's an artifice.
这是一种人为的东西
说到这里 卡尔·荣格 伟大的心理治疗师关于人格说过的一件事是
And having said that, one of the things that Carl Jung, the great psychotherapist said about a persona is, don't be thinking that you're better off if you never formed one.
不要以为如果你从未形成过一个人格 你就会更好
所以对荣格来说 这是一次从婴儿时期的未分化自我通过人格到达真实性的旅程
So for Jung, it was a voyage from say undifferentiated self in infancy and so forth through persona to authenticity, because you have to act out your ideals to some degree,
因为你在某种程度上必须表现出你的理想 对吗？
right, and you also have to formulate a avatar of yourself in some sense, that's a mediator between you and other people in casual social encounters.
你还必须在某种意义上为自己构建一个化身 作为你和其他人在日常社交场合中的中介
比如你不想走进银行 当你问柜员 “你好吗”时 柜员告诉你他或她的这一天怎么样 对吗？（译注：“你好吗”只是一个客套的寒暄 可柜员却真的开始倾诉自己的内心）
Like you don't wanna walk into the bank and have the teller tell you about his or her day when you say, how are you doing, right?
I mean, now and then that can happen, but generally it's too much intimacy too quickly.
我的意思是 这种情况偶尔会发生 但通常它过快地推进关系了
所以你需要这个功能性的外壳
And so you need this functional shell, but the problem arises when that functional shell is all that there is.
但问题出现在 当这个功能性外壳成为全部时
And then the real person underneath is just desperate and unhappy because nothing of what's being acted out reflects a true underlying reality.
然后真实的自我只是绝望和不快乐 因为表现出的一切都没有反映出真实的底层现实 （译注：人格面具理论）
What is the consequence, the long-term consequence of acting?
这种表演的长期后果是什么？
So many people, especially because of the world
因此 很多人 尤其是因为我生活在Instagram和社交媒体的世界里 我们某种程度上构建了这些人格 然后我们几乎跟随这些人格随附的隐含指令？
I live in on Instagram and social media, we kind of build out these personas and then we almost follow the implicit instructions that come with those personas.
So that's the problem right there is that,
那就是问题所在
well, that I'm trying to get a hold of the Disney people at the moment because I wanna do a lecture series on Pinocchio because I think Pinocchio is a brilliant work of art.
我现在正试图联系迪士尼的人 因为我想做一个关于《匹诺曹》的讲座系列 因为我认为《匹诺曹》是一部杰出的艺术作品
And if you're a puppet and an actor, and Pinocchio is both at times in that movie, both a puppet and an actor, so why an actor?
如果你是一个木偶和一个演员 而匹诺曹在那部电影中时而是木偶时而是演员 那么为什么要当一个演员呢？
或者说 为什么当一个演员会有问题呢？
Why is there something wrong with being an actor?
首先 谁设定了你的角色？
Well, the first question is, well, who sets your role?
然后第二个问题是 谁在操纵你？
And then the second question is, who's pulling your strings?
所以你表现出这样一个外表 目的是让你受欢迎、性感、令人渴望 并掩盖你自己的不足
So you've put on this front that is there to make you popular and sexy and desirable and to mask from yourself your own inadequacies, but that's a role.
但那只是一个角色
Well, who wrote it and for what purpose?
那么 谁编写了它 又是为了什么目的？
And so Jung said, for example, that we all acted out a myth and whether we knew it or not.
所以荣格说 比如 我们都在表演一个神话 不管我们是否知道
And you know, maybe you're acting out a tragedy.
你知道 也许你在表演一个悲剧
Maybe you're acting out narcissus.
也许你在表演纳西索斯 （译注：在希腊神话中 "Narcissus" 是一个美丽的青年 因爱上了自己在水中的倒影而成为自恋的象征 他无法抗拒自己倒影的魅力 最终化为一朵水仙花 ）
You don't know because you've put that on yourself in an attempt in some ways to deliver to people what they want or more accurately to look as though you're delivering to people what they want.
你不知道 因为你在尝试以某种方式满足人们的需求 或者更准确地说 看起来像是在满足人们的需求
And it's not nothing to do that, right?
做到这一点并非微不足道 对吧？
Because at least you're attempting in some sense to adapt to the social world.
因为至少你在某种意义上尝试适应社会世界
Someone who's really infantile and dependent, someone who's never left home.
一个真正幼稚和依赖的人 一个从未离家的人
Part of their problem is that they haven't crafted persona
他们的部分问题是他们没有塑造一个人格
所以你不是想完全贬低它 但它无法代替真实的东西
so you don't want to denigrate it entirely but it's no substitute for the real thing and it turns out that not only is what we want from each other the real thing
事实证明 这不仅是我们对彼此的真实需求 而且也是你生命的冒险
but that's also the adventure of your life and so if you aren't truthful and that means unfortunately especially at the beginning when you start to be truthful
因此 如果你不诚实 这意味着不幸的是 尤其是在一开始 当你开始诚实时 这意味着你需要在谦卑中深刻地接受自己的不足
it means deeply coming to terms with your inadequacies in humility so it's very painful
所以这是非常痛苦的
without that you don't have the adventure of your life you have the role that has been that you've acquiesced to and that'll take all the meaning out of your life
没有这个 你就没有你生命的冒险
你所扮演的角色已经是你所默许的 这会让你的生命失去所有的意义
the adventure of your life, you say, imagine who you could be and then aim single-mindedly at that
你生命的冒险
你说 想象一下你可以成为谁 然后一心一意地追求那个目标
我遇到这些年轻人 他们似乎知道自己可以成为什么 或者他们已经想象了自己可以成为什么
I encountered these young people who appear to know who they could be or they've imagined who they could be
but for whatever reason they seem to choose the certain and misery of their current situation, the job that's sucking their soul out or that relationship,
但无论出于何种原因 他们似乎选择了当前处境的某种痛苦
那些吸走他们灵魂的工作 或者那种关系
而不是选择他们在生命冒险中将遇到的不确定性
over the uncertainty they'll encounter as they go on the adventure of their life.
那么我要对那些年轻人 那些总是对我说 史蒂夫 我想做这个
So what would I say to these young people who always say to me, Steve, I wanna do this,
但你可以看到他们被恐惧窒息 因为这就像——是的 好吧 就像 制定一个计划 伙计
but you can see them stifled by fear because it's like- Yeah, well, it's like, make a plan, man.
所以当我在做我的临床工作时
So when I was doing my clinical work,
我和我的来访者做了很多职业工作 包括初级水平的 我想说
which I did a lot of career work with my clients, both at a beginner level, I would say, like really a beginner level with people who had no employment whatsoever, no history of employment, who are undereducated and who lacked every skill you could possibly imagine.
真的是初级水平 对那些根本没有工作经历 没有就业史 受教育程度低 缺乏你能想象到的每一项技能的人
These are people who are really in dire straits, up to people who were operating at the top of their profession, but who could still strategize forward.
这些人真的处境非常艰难 甚至是那些在职业生涯中处于巅峰的人 但（即使是他们）仍然可以制定前进的战略
举个例子 比如你的工作陷入了死胡同
And so, for example, let's say you're at a dead end in your job, okay, so I don't find my work meaningful.
好吧 所以我觉得我的工作没有意义
All right, so that's a problem statement.
好的 那是一个问题陈述
It's like, well, why not?
就像 为什么没有？
I find the work I do repetitive and boring and without spirit.
我发现我做的工作重复且无聊 缺乏灵魂 我和我的老板关系不好或一般般 他都不知道我是谁
I have a bad relationship or a neutral relationship with my boss who doesn't know who I am.
我和同事有问题
I have problems with coworkers.
所有这些都需要被区分开 对吗？
All of that needs to be differentiated, right?
并且需要详细分析
And analyzed in detail.
所以我们可能会说 例如 假设你认为你在工作中被低估了 也许你确实被低估了
So we might say, for example, let's say you believe that you're undervalued at work and maybe you are.
你需要做的是你有话要说 我们需要找出你需要说的是什么
What you need to do is you have something to say and we would have to figure out what it is that you have to say.
但它会是某种变体
But it would be some variant of,
我产出的价值超出了我所获得的补偿
I'm bringing more value to the table than I'm being compensated for.
这让我感到泄气
And that's demoralizing me.
而且对你来说也不好 你是我的老板 因为如果我实际上比被认可的更有价值
And it's also not good for you, you being my boss, because if I'm actually more valuable than is being recognized,
那么你没有正确评价我
then the fact that you're not valuing me properly means that I will become demoralized.
意味着我会变得泄气
I won't work properly and you won't get the best out of me.
我将无法正常工作 你也无法从我这里得到最好的表现
So it's bad for both of us.
所以这对我们双方都不好
And if your boss is in principle, not amenable to such a discussion, then what you should seriously consider doing is finding another job.
如果你的老板原则上不愿意进行这样的讨论 那么你应该认真考虑找一份新工作
Okay, so let's say we're gonna set you up for this.
好 假设我们为此做准备
Okay, this isn't like next week's enterprise, man.
这不是下周的事业 伙计 这是你的生活
This is your life.
所以我首先会问的是 你的简历或CV是否准备好了？（译注：在职业和学术领域中 CV——Curriculum Vitae——是一份详细列出个人教育背景、工作经验、成就、技能和资质的文档 与简历（resume）相比 CV往往更为详细）
So the first thing I would ask is, well, do you have your resume or CV in order?
我已经三年没有打印它了
Well, I haven't typed it up for three years.
好的 要不要考虑把它拾起来 更新一下它
Well, what do you think about bringing it up?
Well, I'm pretty nervous about that because there's some holes in it.
我对此感到相当紧张 因为我的简历上有一些空白 我在大学的成绩不是很好 我对我的简历有点尴尬
And you know, I didn't do so well in college and I'm kind of embarrassed about my resume.
好吧 把它拿来
It's like, okay, bring it in.
我们来仔细看看
Let's go through it.
至少更新一下它
Let's at least update it.
看看哪里有空白
Let's look where the holes are.
看看在你看来哪里有不足之处 对吗？
Let's look at where the inadequacies are as far as you're concerned, right?
这不是我的评判 这是你的评判
This isn't my judgment, it's your judgment.
让我们一起检视这些评判 看看它们是否有根据
Let's walk through those judgments and see if they're warranted
因为也许你只是太感到内疚、羞愧、自我意识过强、焦虑 相比于他人 你更苛刻地看待自己的简历
because maybe you're just too guilty and ashamed and self-conscious and anxious and you're not, you're looking at your resume more critically than someone else would.
也许有些漏洞你需要修补
And maybe there's some holes that you need to rectify.
比如 你还差两门课就能拿到学士学位 但你却退学了
You know, you were two courses away from your BA and you dropped out or something like that.
那么 我们也许需要六个月来解决这个问题
Well, maybe we need six months to address that.
即使你不能完全受教育 你也可以在线上修一些课程
And at least, even if you can't be fully educated, you could be taking some courses online.
And so when you went to a new job interview and they said,
这样当你去面试一个新工作时 他们问到这个漏洞时
What about this whole, you'd say, well, I came to terms with that six months ago and in an effort to rectify it, I'm taking the following courses and here's my plan for completion.
你可以说 六个月前我已经开始着手解决这个问题 为了改正 我正在修以下课程
这是我的完成计划
That's a really good answer.
这是一个很好的回答
And anyone with any sense who's interviewing
任何有理智的面试官都会将其视为一个迹象 尽管你不完美——谁是完美的呢 但你有一个好计划 并且你已经深思熟虑
will accept that as an indication that although you're not perfect and who is that you have a good plan and that you've thought it through.
像这样的回答很有可能会巩固你成为该职位候选人的地位
Like that's the kind of answer that in all likelihood will cement your candidacy for the position.
好的 现在你要去找你的老板了
Okay, so now you're gonna go to your boss.
Well, you have to have your CV and your resume in order, and you have to be able to stand on it solidly,
你必须整理好你的简历和履历
并且你必须能够坚定地站在它上面
and which at least means that you're prepared to address the inadequacies in a credible, realistic, believable, and truthful manner.
至少意味着你准备以一个可信和真实的方式来解决不足
All right, now what you do is apply for like 10 jobs.
好了 现在你做的是申请大概10个工作
You don't have to take them,
你不必全部参加
but maybe you have to go to an interview or two or three or four,
但也许你得去参加一两次或三四次面试
And maybe there's a bunch of opportunities out there for you that you didn't even know about.
也许有很多甚至你自己都不知道的机会在等着你
And maybe someone offers you a job.
也许有人给你提供了一份工作
这样你就可以去找你的老板说
And so now you can go to your boss and say, here's the situation I'm in here at work.
这是我在工作中的处境
Here's my evaluation of the problems in relationship to me.
这是我对与我有关的问题的评估
Here's what I could do for you if you gave me a 40% raise and the opportunity to progress, but I'd like to see a plan for that.
如果你给我40%的加薪和晋升的机会 我可以为你做些什么 但我想看到一个计划
And I've been looking for other opportunities before conducting this discussion and I have some.
在进行这次讨论之前 我一直在寻找其他机会 并且我已经有了一些（机会）
那么 如果这时你的老板对你表现出轻蔑 不听你讲 那么他或她可能比较理想的情况下要更自恋一些
Well, then if your boss treats you with contempt at that point and doesn't listen, then perhaps he or she is a little more narcissistic than might be optimal and it's time to find a new job.
是时候找一份新工作了
但这不是你草率决定的（微不足道的）事情
But this isn't something you do trivially.
And so when you're doubtful, say you're trapped, you ask yourself, well, why am I trapped?
所以 当你感到怀疑 比如你觉得自己被困住了 你要问自己 我为什么会被困？
That's a hard question, right?
这是一个艰难的问题 对吗？
Because some of it's your own inadequacy, a lot of it.
因为有一部分是你自己的不足 很大一部分
And all of the part of it that you can deal with is your own inadequacy.
而你能处理的所有部分就是你自己的不足
So even if it's unfair, you know, even if you're hemmed in for any number of reasons,
所以 即使这是不公平的 你知道 即使你因为任何原因被限制
inappropriate, like ethnically predicated oppression, let's say, or maybe you live it, you're in a workplace that really is sexist in some fundamental sense.
不合适的 比如基于种族的压迫 比方说 或者也许你生活在一个真正有性别歧视的工作环境中
Well, that's not good.
那不好
这不公正 这不公平
It's not just, it's not fair, it's not meritorious, all of those things.
这不是基于成果（评估贡献）的 所有这些
Man, maybe you shouldn't be there.
也许你不应该在那里
But what you can do to begin with is every bloody thing you possibly can do to put yourself in the most virtuous and powerful negotiating position possible.
但你一开始能做的就是尽你所能做的一切 让自己处于最有德性（最有利）和最强大的谈判位置
And you have to think like a snake in some sense.
在某种意义上 你必须像蛇一样思考
To do that, you gotta get the details right.
要做到这一点 你必须正确地把握细节
你必须准备好咬人
You have to be prepared to bite and you have to have your eyes on the prize, so to speak.
你必须把眼光放在奖赏上 可以这么说
And people aren't taught this sort of thing ever, really.
人们从来真的没有被教导过这类事情
They're not taught how to negotiate.
他们没有被教导如何谈判
They're not taught how to goal set.
他们没有被教导如何设定目标
They're not taught how to conceptualize appropriate success in some broad sense.
他们没有被教导如何在某种广泛意义上构想适当的成功
In some sense, that's what the humanities are supposed to teach people, so.
在某种意义上 这是人文学科应该教给人们的
在理解我的不足或某人的不足这一点上 我真的相信
On that point of understanding my inadequacies or someone's inadequacies, I really believe that it's really difficult to undergo self-development if you don't have self-awareness.
如果你没有自我意识 那么你真的很难进行自我发展
And I was really trying to understand from your writings how someone is to build their self-awareness.
我真的在试图从你的著作中理解一个人如何建立他们的自我意识
It's almost like the unknown unknown.
这几乎像是未知的未知
If you don't have it, how do you build the thing?
如果你都不知道它 你怎么能构建它呢？
I know a good exercise for that.
我知道一个好的练习
It's like a prayer in some sense.
这在某种意义上像是祈祷
In fact, I would say it's proper prayer.
实际上 我会说这是正确的祈祷
If you wanna know something about yourself, sit on your bed one night and say to yourself, you gotta mean this, like, you gotta be desperate.
如果你想了解自己的一些事情 某个晚上坐在你的床上对自己说 你得真心这么想 就像 你必须绝望
This is no game, this.
这不是游戏
It's like, my life is not everything I want it to be.
就像 我的生活不是我想要的一切
And perhaps it's not everything that I need it to be.
也许它不是我所需要的一切
而“需要”的意思是 我的生活如此难以忍受 以至于随之而来的痛苦让我变得虚无、愤世嫉俗、痛苦、怨恨
And by need, I mean, my life is so unbearable that the suffering that's attended upon that is make me nihilistic, cynical, bitter, resentful, homicidal, genocidal, unable to have a good relationship,
有杀人倾向、灭绝人性、无法建立良好的关系
倾向于 因为我的嫉妒而惩罚人们的美德
prone to punish people for their virtues because of my jealousy, driving the proclivity to see evil everywhere except within my own heart.
倾向于 目之所及都是邪恶 却不愿意正视自己内心的邪恶
Like these are problems, man.
像这些都是问题 伙计
And you ask yourself, you sit on the bed and say, okay, man, I'm ready to learn something.
你问自己 坐在床上 说 好吧 伙计 我准备学习一些东西
Like, what's one thing I'm doing wrong that I know I'm doing wrong that I could fix that I would fix?
比如 有哪件我做错了的事 我知道我做错了 我能够去修补 我想要去修补
It's like, you meditate on that, you'll get an answer.
你对此进行沉思 你会得到一个答案
And it won't be one you want,
这不会是你想要的答案 但它会是必要的答案
but it'll be the necessary one, you know?
它通常会引导你发现一些细节
And it's often something that will point you to small things.
所以卡尔·荣格说 现代世界的人们看不见上帝 因为他们寻找的视角不够低
So Carl Jung said, people in the modern world don't see God because they don't look low enough.
因此想象你在你杂乱的卧室里
And so imagine you're in your messy bedroom,
你知道 你坐在床边尝试与自己进行诚实的对话
you know, and you're sitting on the edge of the bed trying to have an honest dialogue with yourself.
And the little voice says,
小声音说 你知道 这里真的很恶心
you know, it's pretty disgusting in here.
你想 好吧 我远远高贵（超出）于这种整理我的房间这样的琐碎小事
And you think, well, I'm way above such trivial niceties as organizing my room.
这就是 好吧 那是骄傲 那是傲慢
It's like, well, that's pride, that's arrogance.
如果你不屑于整理真正属于你的东西
If you're above organizing what's actually yours,
你怎么可能整理其他任何东西呢？
how in the world are you ever gonna organize anything else?
所以你跪下 思考
And so you get on your knees and you think,
好吧 是时候拿起刷子刷厕所了 也许这就是你开始的地方
well, it's time to take a brush to the toilet and maybe that's where you start.
这样做是有效的 确实有效
And so, and that works, like that works.
你开始做这些微小的改进 像真正的微小改进 真正的实际操作
You start making those micro improvements, like real micro improvements, real on the ground,
对你知道是错误的事情进行实际的微小改进
actual micro improvements to things you know that are wrong, you'll improve unbelievably rapidly.
你会难以置信地快速改进
好 你谈论这个
Well, you're talking about this, sounds to me a lot like an over dose of arrogance and also the need for humility.
在我听来很像是过度的傲慢以及需要谦卑
Do you think the Western world suffers from arrogance because of our relative privilege and luxury that we kind of overlook?
你认为西方世界因为我们所忽视的相对特权和奢侈而遭受傲慢之苦吗？
Of course, well, that's a temptation, right?
当然 这是一种诱惑 对吗？
I mean, when the left radical lefty types go after people for their unearned privilege, they have a point.
我的意思是 当左派激进分子因为份外的特权而攻击人们时 他们有一点道理
Now, the point is the existentialists called it throne-ness, which is not, that's a Heideggerian term.
现在 存在主义者称之为“被抛” 这是海德格的术语
And throne-ness is the fact that we kind of experience life as if we're tossed into it, thrown into it.
被抛是指我们仿佛被投入到生活中、被抛入到生活中 去经历生活
You know, you're male and not female.
你知道 你是男性而非女性
You're Hindu and not Christian.
你是印度教徒而非基督徒
You're tall and not short.
你个子高而不是矮
You have an arbitrary range of talents and an arbitrary range of limitations, none of which in some sense you chose.
你有一系列随机的才能和一系列随机的限制 从某种意义上说 这些都不是你选择的
It's the cards you're dealt.
这就是你被发的牌
Now, some of those are cards of privilege.
现在 其中一些是特权牌
Now, maybe you're born intelligent.
也许你天生聪明
Maybe you're born symmetrical.
也许你天生匀称
Maybe you're born healthy.
也许你天生健康
Maybe you're born into a culture where it's much easier not to be absolutely deprived.
也许你出生在一个不极端贫困的文明中
Maybe your parents are rich.
也许你的父母很富有
And so all of that in some sense is unearned.
所以所有这些在某种意义上都是份外的
现在 随之而来的是大量的存在性负罪感 因为同时 这对任何人来说都是如此
Now, along with that comes a good dose of existential guilt because at the same time, and this is true for anyone, regardless of their cultural background,
无论他们的文化背景如何 我们走过的地面都浸透了历史暴行的血迹
the ground we walk on is soaked in the blood of historical atrocity.
所以这就落在了你身上 因为人们想知道 谁是纳粹？
And so that's on you because people think, well, who's the Nazi?
谁是法西斯 或者谁是激进的共产主义者
Well, it's the fascist or it's the, or who's the radical communist.
谁是激进的左翼意识形态者
It's the radical left-wing ideologue.
事实上 最好将其视为一个精神问题 最深刻的敌人其实在内心
And the fundamental truth of the matter is that's best dealt with as a spiritual matter, is the adversary is within really most profoundly.
因此 你必须将那些历史上的暴行的责任承担在自己身上
And so you have to take the responsibility for that historical atrocity onto yourself.
我本周与盖·里奇讨论了他的电影《亚瑟王》
I was talking to Guy Ritchie this week about his movie, King Arthur.
这部电影在许多方面都颇为有趣
It's quite an interesting movie in many ways.
当可能成为英雄的亚瑟拿起这把剑时 他被他凶残的叔叔的幻象所困扰 以至于无法拿起武器
And when Arthur, who could be the hero, takes the sword, he's so overcome by visions of his murderous uncle that he can't pick up the weapon.
想想看
Well, think about that.
现在你有可以使用的武器 但它们曾经被你那杀人犯的叔叔使用过
Now you have weapons at your disposal, but they've been used by your murderous uncle.
你怎么敢使用它们？
How dare you wield them?
答案是
And the answer is,
也许把剑留在地上更简单 因为你确实不想为未来可能发生的暴行负责 也不以为你不可能会这样 也不以为你可能不会对此感到愉快
maybe it's easy just to leave the sword on the ground because you do wanna be responsible for atrocities going forward and don't think you couldn't be and don't think you might not enjoy it.
因此 你为自己的特权付出的代价就是你的美德
And so the way you pay for your privilege is with your virtue.
而我尤其认为
I mean that most particularly.
你有这些机会和这种存在性的罪恶感
You have these opportunities and this existential guilt and the way you expiate that and atone
is by doing your best to live the best possible life you can manage, to speak the truth,
而你弥补的方式就是 尽你最大的努力过上你能做到的最好的生活 说真话 尊重他人
to treat people with respect,
遵守个人尊严的原则 并且整理好你的家务
to abide by the principles of the dignity of the individual and to put your house in order.
这就是你为你份外的特权付出的代价 我们所有人都是这样
And that's how you pay for your unearned privilege, all of us.
我们都有我们的特权和诅咒 对吧
And we all have our privileges and our curses, you know?
我们所有人都有
All of us have that.
这就是为什么嫉妒别人是没有用的
That's why it's not useful to be envious of people.
你知道 你是个年轻人 你看到有人开着法拉利经过 旁边坐着个金发美女 你想 我的天 他拥有一切
You know, you see some, you're a young man, you see someone drive by in a Ferrari with blonde and you think, my God, he's got everything.
但 车里的女人是个可卡因成瘾的妓女 她的生活是一个又一个的灾难
And you know, the woman in the car is a prostitute who's got a cocaine addiction and her life is just one catastrophe after another.
而开车的人可能不得不通过欺骗和作弊来达到这个位置
And he's had to lie and cheat his way into this position.
他害怕一切都会崩溃 砸在他身上
And he's afraid that everything's going to come crashing down on him.
而这就是你嫉妒的
And that's what you're jealous of.
这其实并不那么深刻
And it's just not that profound.
你不想要别人的命运
You don't want someone else's fate.
伙计 你的命运就够了 你的冒险就够了
Man, your fate's enough and your adventure's enough.
这已经很多了
It's plenty.
这比你能完全实现的还要多
It's more than you can ever fully realize.
因此 这也是我们所有人都相信个体具有某种内在尊严的部分原因
And so that's also part of the reason that we all believe that the individual has some intrinsic dignity.
不要那么笃定你的位置和你的房间是那么无足轻重
It's don't be so sure that your position and your room is so damn trivial.
也许是你把他们当作琐碎的、微不足道的小事来对待
It might be your attitude towards it that's trivial.
如果你处于困境和恶劣的环境
And if you're in dire straits and dire circumstances,
只要看看你有多少机会让事情变得更好
just look at how much opportunity you have to make things better.
所以这并不容易
So not that it's easy.
你甚至不希望它变得容易
You don't even want it to be easy.
不 所以
No, so.
关于这一点 “你不希望它变得容易” 我真的一直在与我生活中的斗争和混乱的想法以及它所扮演的角色作斗争
On that point of you don't want it to be easy, I really contended with this idea of struggle and chaos in my life and the role it plays.
And once upon a time, I thought I was trying to rid my life of chaos and struggle.
曾几何时 我以为我试图从生活中清除混乱和斗争
我以为这就是我试图变得富有、得到法拉利和金发女郎的原因
I thought that's why I was trying to get rich and get the Ferrari and the blonde.
我以为那会创造一个没有斗争的生活
I thought that would create a life free of struggle.
但后来我看了一些研究 听说了一个叫做“金牌抑郁症”的东西 当奥运会运动员从奥运会回来后 他们失去了方向感
But then I looked at some studies and I heard about this thing called gold medal depression when Olympians come back from the Olympics and they've lost orientation.
然后有一天 当有人提出以八、九位数的价格购买我的公司时
And then the day when someone offered to buy my company for a eight, nine, nine figure number.
它让我感到了空虚和恐惧
And it filled me with this emptiness and this dread.
And I tried to understand the role that struggle would have to play for me to be a fulfilled human being for the rest of my life.
我试图理解对于我在余生成为一个充实的人 “斗争”在其中所扮演的角色
Yeah, well, the observation with regard to your company, that's a great observation.
是的 关于你的公司的观察 这是一个伟大的观察
我的意思是 我们生来就是为了向上攀爬
I mean, we're built to walk uphill.
And when you reach the pinnacle of the hill, you want to stop and appreciate the vision.
当你到达山顶时 你想停下来欣赏景色 但接下来你想要的是远处更高的山 因为正是从向上攀爬中 我们获得了我们的价值
But the next thing you want is a higher hill in the distance because it's the uphill climb that it's from the uphill climb that we derive our value.
我是从技术上讲的
And I mean this technically.
So almost all the positive emotion we feel,
因此 几乎所有我们感受到的正面情绪 尤其是让我们充满热情的情绪 那就是被上帝灵充满 因为这就是热情的含义
especially the emotion that fills us with enthusiasm, and that's to be filled with the Spirit of God, by the way, because that's what enthusiasm means,
that's experienced in relationship to a goal.
那是与目标有关的经历
因此 在某种意义上 这是宗教事业的一部分
And so in some sense, and this is part of the religious enterprise, you want a goal that you can never attain, right?
你想要一个你永远无法达到的目标 对吧？
这样你就可以不断接近一个随着你接近而后退的目标
So you can always move closer to the goal that recedes as you move towards it.
你可能会觉得这很挫败
You think, well, that's frustrating.
这就像西西弗斯推石头上山
It's like Sisyphus pushing the rock uphill.
但并非如此 因为当你追求那个目标时
But it's not because as you pursue that goal,
你整合了自己 你的生活确实变得更好、更丰富、更充裕
you put yourself together and your life does get better and richer and more abundant.
这就是为什么最高层次的美德和目标在某种意义上是超越的
And that's why the highest levels of virtue and goal are in some sense transcendent.
你希望它们超越你正在做的一切 这样你就可以不断向着更崇高、更好的东西前进
You want them to be above everything you're doing so you can continually move towards something that's more sublime and better.
这就是你
That's what you are.
你在这里是为了生活 而不是为了睡觉
You're here to live, not to sleep.
And the problem with the vision of my ties on the beach is that, well, first of all,
在海滩上穿西装的愿景的问题是 首先 那是药物诱导的无意识状态的愿景
that's a vision of drug-induced unconsciousness.
其次 这只会持续大约一个星期
Second, it's only gonna work for about a week.
第三 一个月后你会成为笑柄 心情沮丧、漫无目的和没有目标
Third, you're gonna be a laughing stock in a month and depressed and aimless and goal-less.
It's, no, that's not, it's, you want a horizon of ever expanding possibility.
不 那不是 你想要一个不断扩展可能性的视野
And so it does happen to people as they,
所以它确实发生在人们身上
因为他们把灵魂押注在了实现一个工具性（手段性）的目标上
because they've staked their soul on the attainment of an instrumental goal.
这可以是一个相当高阶的目标
And it can be a pretty high order goal, it was in your case, but then you think,
在你的案例中就是这样
但然后你想 好吧 现在我在这里了 接下来呢？
well, now I'm there, now what?
Well, the answer can't be,
答案不会是
well, I'm going to live in the lap of luxury and never have to leave the, what do you wanna be, a giant infant with a gold bottle?
我将生活在奢侈中 永远不必离开 你想成为什么 一个拿着金瓶的巨婴吗？
你永远不需要做任何事情 只需要躺在背上吸吮
You never have to do anything but lay in your back and suck.
就像 嗯 你可以看到这个问题是一个概念化的问题
It's like, well, you see the problem with that as a conceptualization.
It's no, you wanna be like an active warrior moving uphill with your sword in hand.
你想成为一个手持宝剑向山上进发的自发的战士
那是充满活力的 那是令人兴奋的
And that's dynamic, that's exciting.
And that's why so many young men disappear into video games.
这就是为什么这么多年轻人沉迷于电子游戏的原因
That's all acted out in the video game.
那一切都在视频游戏中表现出来了 （译注：在游戏中 玩家体验到这种冒险、向前的经历）
So they have to act that out in their own life.
所以他们必须在自己的生活中表现出来
不是我看不起视频游戏 但它们不能替代生活
Not that I despise video games, because I don't, but they're not a substitute for life.
They might be good training under some conditions for life.
它们在某些条件下可能是生活的不错的训练
我还特别想问你的是 过去两年世界上发生的事情
One of the things I was also really, really keen to ask you was about what's happened in the world over the last two years.
我们在商业世界中看到的变化之一是向远程工作的转变
One of the shifts we've seen in the business world is this move to remote working and I hate it.
我讨厌它 出于各种原因我讨厌它 因为我感觉在我的生活中很少有机构让我有机会与人真正意义上的连接
And I hate it for a variety of reasons because I feel like there's very few institutions
in my life where I have a chance to meaningfully connect with people.
约会变成了屏幕
Dating has become screens.
社交变成了屏幕
Socializing has become screens.
办公室 办公室在我的生活中是我——特别是作为一个年轻人+几乎是我遇到90%当前最好的朋友以及伴侣的地方之一
And the office, the institution of the office in my life was one of the places, especially as a younger man,
where I got to meet pretty much 90% of my current best friends and also partners.
我真的很担心未来 10 年坐在 Zoom 后面工作 （译注：Zoom 是一个流行的视频会议和远程沟通软件 广泛用于个人和企业之间的在线会议、远程工作、虚拟教育课堂、网络研讨会等）
And I really worry about sitting behind a Zoom, doing my work for the next 10 years.
What is your take on remote working?
你对远程工作有什么看法？
Well, I like it and I don't like it.
嗯 我既喜欢也不喜欢
I think it's very difficult for us to understand our embodied environments well enough to duplicate them in a healthy and comprehensive manner in the virtual world.
我认为我们很难充分理解我们的现实环境 从而在虚拟世界中以健康、全面的方式复制它们
Because we just don't understand what it is that we're doing when we actually do things rather than represent them.
我们在真正做事情而不仅仅是表达它们时 往往不理解我们所做的事情的本质（译注：在许多情况下 人们可能会理论化或想象某种行为的效果 但在实际行动时 结果和影响可能与预期大相径庭 因为实际操作涉及的变量和复杂性远远超出了理论上的考量）
So for example, I've thought a lot about online university.
例如 我对线上大学思考了很多
Okay, so then you could imagine,
好吧 那么你可以想象
well, you can certainly imagine online lecture courses.
线上讲座课程肯定是可以想象的
And you could say, well, the fact that they can be delivered on a large scale, very inexpensively, is a virtue.
你可以说 它们的好处是 可以大规模地、非常便宜地提供
You can bring the knowledge to a very large number of people at a low cost, so why not do that?
你可以以低成本为大量人群带来知识 那么为什么不这样做呢？
And so that's half the university.
所以那是大学的一半
And then you could say, well, imagine that you generated the system of universal tests, which is possibility,
然后你可以说 想象你生成了一套普遍测试系统（译注：全面实施的测试体系 类似于考核、测试） 这是可能的 这意味着你也可以以低成本为每个人带来认证
and that means you could bring accreditation to everyone at a low cost as well.
And that's that.
那么 大学就在线上了
The university's online.
但这个过程是你假设自己知道大学是什么 但你实际上不知道
But that presumes that you know what the university is and you don't because well here's some other things the university is
因为 嗯 大学还有其他一些东西
An excuse for young a credible excuse that socially sanctioned for young people who have not yet established a career goal
一个可信的、社会认可的理由 让尚未确立职业目标的年轻人树立向上奋斗的身份
To adopt an identity of upward striving for four years away from their parents while they meet a new group of friends
在他们离开父母四年的同时 他们遇见了一群新朋友
Like that might be 90% of the university for all we know, because it's certainly, for me, for example,
就像这可能是大学的90% 因为这对我来说 例如
when I went to college, I left home when I was 17 and I left this small town I had grown up in.
当我上大学时 我17岁就离家出走 离开了我长大的小镇
And in many ways, I left the peers that I had been associating with.
在许多方面 我离开了我一直交往的同龄人
Now, a couple of them came to college with me.
现在 他们中的几个和我一起上了大学 所以我在那里有了一个立足点
So I had a toehold there, but I made an entirely different group of friends.
但我结交了完全不同的一群朋友
And they were friends whose goals were quite radically different from the friends that I, let's say, in some sense, left behind.
在某种意义上 这些朋友的目标与我之前的朋友的目标完全不同
Well, the reformulation of my peer network might've been the most important part of the first part of my education.
重组我的同伴网络可能是我教育的第一部分中最重要的一部分
现在 我在这个地方很幸运
Now, I was fortunate at this place, it was called Grand Prairie College.
它被称为大草原城地区学院
I had seven professors, seven, which is really good, who really loved to teach.
我有七位教授 七位 这真的很棒 他们真正热爱教学
And so I also learned a lot in the formal sense.
因此我也在正式的意义上学到了很多东西
但在我做这些的同时 我也在谈判
But while I was doing that, I was also negotiating,
比如 你实际上应该聚会多少呢？
well, how much partying do you actually do?
因为零不是正确的数量
Cause zero isn't the right amount,
但是每个该死的晚上直到凌晨三点也不是正确的数量 因为你必须在现实和向上努力之间取得平衡
but every goddamn night till three in the morning isn't the right amount either because you have to balance that in some sense with practicality and upward striving.
那么 我该如何与他人生活？
And so, and how do I live with other people?
我的室友 所以我有一个室友 他仍然是我的好朋友 今年我生病的时候 他字面上和我一起走了一千英里
My roommate, so I had one roommate who's a really good friend of mine still, and he walked a thousand miles with me this year when I was ill, literally.
所以我真的很喜欢和他一起生活 因为他是个硬汉
So I really liked living with him because he was tough guy,
在铅冶炼厂工作 他是个牛仔 他是个硬汉 比我大四岁 大约大三岁
worked in lead smelters and he was a cowboy and he was a tough guy, four years older than me, about three years older than me.
在经历了这些艰苦的工人阶级职业之后 他回到学校
He'd come back to school after bouncing around through these like tough working class occupations.
他在很多方面都很脚踏实地
And he had his feet on the ground in lots of ways.
我真的很喜欢他作为室友 因为我会买一些食材 然后他也会买一些食材 或者我做晚饭 他做早餐
And I really liked him as a roommate because I'd buy some groceries and then he'd buy some groceries or I'd make dinner and he'd make breakfast.
这一切都从未明确地商议过
And none of that was ever explicitly negotiated.
他对这种互惠的 从技术上讲是互利的行为非常清楚
He was just very aware of this reciprocal, it's reciprocal altruism technically.
他非常擅长 我们俩都擅长认识到我们的相互义务并履行它们
He was very good at, we were both good at tracking our mutual obligations and fulfilling them.
So we had a very peaceful relationship.
所以我们的关系非常和平
I lived with him for a year and then a little bit at different times and in different places.
我和他住了一年 然后在不同的时间和不同的地方又住了一段时间
And I learned to live with a whole variety of roommates.
我学会了与各种各样的室友共处
I had many roommates.
我有很多室友
We had a kind of a frat house in the first college I went to and I think anywhere from six to 20 people lived there depending on the week, you know.
我们在我去的第一所大学有一种类似兄弟会的房子 我想那里住着的人数根据周而定 大约从六到二十人不等
It was really, it was ridiculous.
这真的很荒谬
It was way too much fun.
那是太多的乐趣了 这也是个问题
And that was also a problem.
但当我回顾我生命中的那段时间时 我肯定不能把教育经历简化为虚拟课程和虚拟测试
But when I look back on that time in my life, I certainly can't reduce the educational experience to virtual classes and virtual tests.
That's maybe that's 10% of it.
也许那只占10%
And we don't know how to replicate those environments that are so formative,
我们不知道如何复制那些如此有形成作用的环境 特别是它们的日常性 你知道吗？
especially in their everydayness, you know,
因为你和你的室友一起生活
because you live with your roommates.
That's a 24 hour thing.
那是24小时的事情
And so the problem with virtualization is that we don't understand our environments well enough
因此 虚拟化的问题在于 当我们只关注我们认为概念上重要的内容时 我们对环境的了解不够充分 无法确定我们没有排除一些重要的东西
to be certain that we're not excluding something vital when we concentrate only on what we think conceptually is important.
现在 我和我儿子定期见面 为了我们正在进行的一个项目
Now, I meet with my son pretty regularly for a project we're working on,
这是一个应用程序 将在人们写作和使用它时教会他们如何写作
which is an app that will teach people to write while they write and use it.
所以我们对此非常兴奋 但我每周和他线上见面一次
So we're quite excited about this, but I meet with him virtually once a week.
这实际上非常高效
And it's actually very efficient.
他出现在屏幕上
He's on the screen.
我们可以看到我们的项目就在我们面前
We can see our project in front of us.
我们可以共同编辑一些基础的教育材料
We can do mutual editing of some of the underlying material, educational material.
现实中也有对应的地点
There's a real place for it.
我在多伦多北部有一个小屋 我们在那里设立了一个类似你这里的工作室
And I have a cottage up north in Toronto where we've set up a studio like your studio here, although ours isn't quite as impressive.
虽然我们的工作室没那么令人印象深刻
但我可以与世界上任何地方的任何人进行采访和讨论
But I can have an interview and discussion with anyone anywhere in the world, even in a foreign language.
甚至是用外语
And that's like unbelievably remarkable.
这真的非常了不起
But that doesn't mean that we know how to virtualize reality or that we should flee into it, right?
但这并不意味着我们知道如何虚拟化现实 或者我们应该逃避现实 对吗？
And these new technologies, they're unbelievably radical and they're very hard to master.
这些新技术是非常激进的 它们很难掌握
And so we all have to be careful and try to keep our feet on the ground to some degree when we're using them.
因此 当我们使用它们时 我们都必须小心并尽量保持脚踏实地
So for example, now I've really only figured this out in the last three months.
例如 现在我真的只是在过去三个月里才弄明白这一点
I get up and I do a series of exercises that my wife taught me that are based in the Kundalini yoga tradition.
我起床后会做一系列我妻子教我的练习 这些练习基于昆达里尼瑜伽传统 非常有帮助
That's real helpful, flexibility and breathing exercises.
柔韧性和呼吸练习 这可以减少我白天的焦虑 我会说大约减少了25%
That reduces my anxiety during the day, I would say about 25%.
然后我会保留一些时间用于写作或从事一些艺术项目
And then I try to reserve some time either for writing or I'm working on a number of artistic projects.
所以我会在早上花几个小时做这些事情 然后可能和我妻子散步或吃早餐 我会在这期间吃早餐
And so I'm going to do one or those for a couple hours in the morning and then maybe a walk or something with my wife and breakfast, I have breakfast during all this.
然后我可以转向互联世界、电子邮件和播客等等
And then I can turn to the sort of connected world email and the podcasts and so forth.
所以隐私和内向隐私之间存在着这种平衡 比方说
And so there's this balance between privacy, introverted privacy, let's say,
并与除了我妻子之外的所有人断绝联系
and disconnect from everyone except for my wife,
然后再有意识地重新连接到虚拟世界
and then a contemplated reconnection with the virtual world.
这似乎效果相当不错
That seems to be working out pretty well.
You wanna get a balance of that that's actually, to use a terrible cliche, sustainable.
你想要达到这种平衡 实际上 用一个可怕的陈词滥调来说 是可持续的 对吧 所以你想要努力追求你的项目
So you wanna hit your projects hard,
但你必须留出时间来 不是用于娱乐 而是用于文化 因为这两者不是一回事
But you have to leave in that, not with entertainment, but with culture, because those are not the same thing.
娱乐是对文化的一种近似
Entertainment is an approximation to culture.
And you need to leave in that with culture.
你需要用文化来填补它 那是美、戏剧、艺术等等 然后是亲密关系和友谊
That's beauty and drama and art and all of that.
And then with intimate relationships and friendships.
And well, it's very difficult to get the balance of all that correct.
而在虚拟环境中很难正确地平衡所有这些 这很难做到
And it's very difficult to do that virtually.
So, but I certainly wouldn't forego the technology and neither would the rest of us.
但我肯定不会放弃技术 我们其他人也不会
It's like people complain about their phones, but they carry them with them everywhere they go.
就像人们抱怨他们的手机 但他们到处都带着它们 对此我并不愤世嫉俗
And I'm not cynical about that.
电话不只是电话
The phone, it's not a phone.
天知道它是什么
God only knows what it is, but it's definitely not a phone.
但它绝对不是电话
因此 不奇怪的是 既然它刚刚出现而且如此强大 我们不知道如何使用它 甚至可能会毁掉一切
And so it's not surprising that since it just appeared and it's so insanely powerful that we don't know what to do with it and that might even wreck everything.
Like God only knows.
就像 只有上帝知道 推特本身就可能让文明停滞不前
Twitter itself could bring civilization to a halt.
我们不知道如何应对我们的技术实力带来的意外后果
We don't know how to manage the unintended consequences of our technological prowess.
这正是问题所在
And that's exactly it.
我们经常发明技术 似乎是为了提高效率或增加生产力
It's the, we invent technology often it seems for efficiency or to increase productivity.
由于对意外后果可能是什么的无知 提前预测它们几乎是不可能的
And it's almost impossible because of that ignorance to what the unintended consequences might be to predict them ahead of time.
所以我们优化——保守派政治哲学的本质学说 对吧 就是要提防意想不到的后果
So we optimize- Essential doctrine of conservative political philosophy, right, is beware of unintended consequences.
It's like, oh no, this thing will just do what I want it to do and nothing else.
就像 “哦 不 这东西只会按我预期的方式工作 不会有其他结果 ”
就像 不 即使是马克思也知道这不是真的
It's like, no, even Marx knew that wasn't true.
马克思发展了异化的概念
Marx developed a concept, the concept of alienation.
你知道 我们会对我们努力的产物感到疏远
We get alienated from the products of our effort.
这部分是他不喜欢工厂的原因
That's part of the reason he didn't like factories.
公平地说 你知道 因为工厂工作是重复性的 在某种意义上 它破坏了我们与我们生产的产品的手工艺关系
And fair enough, because factory work, which is repetitive, in some sense, destroys our artisanal relationship with what we produce.
现在 马克思分析的问题是
Now, the problem with Marx's analysis is that,
是的 但这非常高效 并且能够很快地将人们从绝对贫困中解救出来
yeah, but it's pretty damn efficient and it lifts people out of absolute poverty really quickly.
但这并不意味着马克思之后的存在主义哲学家将异化概念发展到相当高的程度
But that doesn't mean that an existential philosophers after Marx developed the concept of alienation to quite a high degree.
技术确实因其人造性、冷漠和机械性质使我们感到疏远 所有这些
And technology does alienate us because of its artificiality and its coldness and its mechanistic nature, all of that.
嗯 我们必须明智地应对这一切
And while we have to contend with that wisely And then you ask, well, how do you contend with things wisely?
然后你会问 怎样才能明智地应对事物？
我会说 不要用欺骗污染你的思想
And I would say, well, don't pollute your thoughts with deceit.
你妥协了你自己的智慧
You compromise your own wisdom.
你将如何做出明智的决策 而不是仅仅是聪明的决策
How are you gonna make intelligent, not intelligent decisions, wise decisions?
这就是为什么你不该说谎
That's why you shouldn't lie.
就像你在扭曲你在这个世界上的定位机制
It's like you're warping the mechanism that orients you in the world.
你真的想这样做吗？
Do you really wanna do that?
这是一个残酷的世界 伙计
This is a brutal world, man.
我在我的临床实践中看到了这一点
And I've seen this in my clinical practice.
那些房子建立在沙子基础上的人 当风开始吹 洪水开始上涨时 他们遇到了如此大的麻烦 非常大的麻烦
People whose houses are built on foundations of sand and the wind starts to blow and the floods start to rise and they are in such trouble, such trouble.
如果你幸运 当某些可怕的事情来临时 你相对诚实 你的关系处于良好状态 也许你不会落入地狱
If you're lucky and something terrible comes your way and you're reasonably honest and your relationships are in good order, maybe you won't end up in hell.
我说的是地狱 我不是说死亡
And I mean hell, I don't mean death.
在很多情况下 你可能会让自己陷入这样的境地：甚至死亡都比你正在经历的事情要好得多
There's lots of situations you can get yourself in where death would be far preferable to what you're going through.
So you need to be afraid of that.
所以你需要对此感到害怕
It's like, don't lie.
就像 不要说谎
In my clinical practice in 20 years, working with every sort of person you could imagine,
在我20年的临床实践中 与你能想象的各种人合作
I never ever saw anyone get away with anything even once.
我从来没有见过有任何人能逃脱惩罚 哪怕一次
So yeah, we're all subject, not least to the judgment of our own conscience.
所以是的 我们所有人都受到至少我们自己良心的审判
Try to escape from that.
尝试逃避它
No one can escape from that.
但没有人能逃避它
过去两年里 世界经历了这场大流行
Over the last two years, the world has gone through this pandemic.
对很多人来说 这是第一次
for a lot of people, this is the first time,
especially for a certain generation, this is the first time they've experienced such unpredictable tectonic destabilization in their lives.
对于某一代人来说 这是他们一生中第一次经历如此不可预测的构造性不稳定
Like I didn't even believe society was something that could close.
我甚至不相信社会是可以停滞的
I didn't believe the tech,
我甚至不知道在我的生意下面有构造性的板块 它们可以关闭我的生意 对吗？
I didn't even know there was tectonic plates under my business that could shut down my business, right?
And also in your, over the last two years, you've undergone some really, you know, I don't even know what the right adjective is to use to-
而且在过去的两年里 你也经历了一些真的 我甚至不知道用什么形容词
构造性这个词还不错
Tectonic's not bad.
那我就用构造性吧
We'll go with tectonic then.
Sure.
Tectonic, you know, unfortunate challenges, I'll say, in your life, but also, you know, with your family.
构造性 你知道 不幸的挑战 我会说在你的生活中 但也 你知道 还有你的家人
What are the lessons we learn from the pandemic and from that type of tectonic suffering about what actually matters in our lives?
我们从这场大流行病和这种结构性的痛苦中学到了哪些关于我们生活中真正重要的事情的教训？
好吧 我们会看看大流行的情况 尽管从某种意义上说 它在某些方面已经结束了
Well, we'll see with regard to the pandemic, because although in some sense it is in some ways over, our reaction to it is by no means over.
我们对它的反应还没有结束 我们反应过度的部分原因是 我们天真地对这样的事情没有做好准备
And part of the reason that we overreacted, I would say so precipitously to it, is that we were unprepared for such things in our naivety.
And then we rushed to imitate a totalitarian society in the immediate aftermath of the pandemic emergence.
然后我们在灾难发生后立即急于模仿极权社会 大流行的出现 这是每个人都应该思考的事情
And that's something that everybody should think about a lot.
And we're not done with all that totalitarian nonsense yet.
我们还没有结束所有那些极权主义的胡说八道
A lot of that's driven by, well, fear and naivety.
很多这样的情况是由恐惧和天真驱动的
I mean, 50% of Democrats in the United States believe you have a 50% chance of being hospitalized with COVID and 25% of Republicans believe the same thing.
我的意思是 50%的美国民主党人认为你有50%的机会因COVID而住院 25%的共和党人也有相同的看法
And you can point a finger at people and laugh at their ignorance, but you should really ask, well, why is this overestimate of that magnitude and what does that mean in relationship to policy?
你可以指着人们笑他们的无知 但你真的应该问 为什么会有这样的高估？
这对政策有什么意义？
And I've had conversations with people advising at the highest level of government, in particularly in Canada, who've told me flat out,
我与一些在政府最高层提供建议的人进行了对话 特别是在加拿大 他们直言不讳地告诉我 他们有非常可靠的消息来源
and they're very reliable sources, that none of the COVID policy for the last year was driven by reliance on science.
过去一年的COVID政策没有依靠科学
It's all opinion poll.
全都是民意调查
这真的很有害 因为
And that's really pernicious because, well, who's asking the questions and how did they set up the answer?
那么 谁在提出问题 他们是如何设置答案的？
And who's answering and in what emotional state?
谁在回答 他们处于什么情绪状态
And so to what degree are we led by considerations of short-term propitiation of unwarranted fear?
那么 我们在多大程度上是被对短期平息无根据恐惧的考虑所引导？
Well, that's no way for free people to live.
这不是自由人民该过的生活方式
It certainly won't work in the long run.
从长远来看 这肯定行不通
We're already seeing tremendous supply chain disruptions and likely the emergence of an inflationary pressure that we haven't experienced since the 1970s in the aftermath of the oil shocks.
我们已经看到巨大的供应链中断 可能出现自1970年代石油危机之后我们未曾经历过的通胀压力
And none of that has sorted itself out yet.
所有这些还没有解决
I believe that we will conclude that our response to the pandemic caused more death and misery than the pandemic itself.
我相信我们最终会得出结论 我们对大流行病的反应而造成的死亡和痛苦比大流行病本身还要多
这场游戏还没有结束
And we have no end game in sight.
我问与我交谈的人的另一件事是 这件事什么时候结束？
Another thing I asked the people that I was speaking with, it's like, when is this over?
Well, we don't know.
嗯 我们不知道
那么 到底会是什么样子呢？
What would over look like?
嗯 我们真的不知道
Well, we don't really know.
现在你看到的是 几乎每个月都有坚持称出现了一个新的、截然不同的变种
And now what you see is this insistence on about a monthly basis that a new and radically different variant has emerged.
And this virus, viruses mutate all the time, but this virus particularly mutates,
这种病毒 病毒一直在变异 但这种病毒特别容易变异
and there are small mutations and medium-sized mutations, numbers, let's say, and also effect, and larger scale mutations.
有小的变异和中等大小的变异 数量上的 也有影响上的和更大规模的变异
When is that a variant?
什么时候算是一个变种？
Well, how about whenever it's convenient for the pharmaceutical companies?
嗯 是不是最有利于制药公司的时候呢
想想 那是愤世嫉俗的
Think, well, that's cynical.
It's, is it now?
现在是吗？
The biggest lawsuits in the history of the American judicial system have been levied against the largest pharmaceutical companies on a regular basis for the last 20 years.
过去 20 年来 美国司法系统历史上规模最大的诉讼经常针对最大的制药公司提起
And since when has it been a proposition of the political left that pharmaceutical companies necessarily have our best interests in mind?
从什么时候 左翼政治人士开始提出制药公司必然考虑到我们的最大利益？
Now, I'm not particularly cynical about pharmaceutical companies.
现在 我对制药公司并不特别愤世嫉俗
I think they have a hard job, both in terms of research and development and marketing and sales.
我认为他们的工作很艰难 无论是在研究和开发方面 还是在市场营销和销售方面
And they're going to do what they can to market and sell.
他们会尽力进行市场推广和销售
But that doesn't mean that they are now to be the arbiters of all public policy
但这并不意味着他们现在要成为所有公共政策的仲裁者 因为我们的政治家太懦弱
because our politicians are too cowardly and incompetent to do anything but devolve their responsibilities to so-called experts, domain experts.
无能到只能将他们的责任推卸给所谓的专家、领域专家
Politics is not public health.
政治不是公共卫生 那是医学
That's medicine.
Politics is the art of analyzing the entire situation and charting a course forward, all things considered.
政治是一门综合考虑一切因素来分析整个局势并规划前进方向的艺术
And for politicians to trot out the experts and say follow the science just means that they've abdicated their own responsibilities.
政治家们推出专家并说 “遵循科学” 这意味着他们放弃了自己的责任
And I think it's appalling.
我认为这很骇人听闻
I mean, I'm not convinced that the evidence that masks work is scientifically credible.
我的意思是 我并不相信口罩有效的证据在科学上是可信的
It's certainly at least doubtful.
它至少是值得怀疑的
And that's just masks.
而且那只是个口罩
I read a paper the other day suggesting that to prevent the transmission of one case of COVID, you have to lock down a thousand people.
我前几天读到一篇论文 建议为了阻止一例COVID的传播 你必须封锁一千人
Like how is that justifiable?
这怎么是合理的呢？
尤其是考虑到COVID的死亡率实际上相当低
Especially given that the mortality rate of COVID is actually quite low unless you have a pre-existent health problem, particularly obesity,
除非你有已经存在的健康问题 特别是肥胖 虽然老龄也算作大多数疾病的风险因素 但并非全部
and although old age also qualifies as it does for most diseases, but not all.
就儿童疫苗接种问题来说 孩子们死于COVID的几率极低
And with regards to let's say the issue of child vaccination is like children have an unbelievably tiny chance of dying from COVID.
我认为对12岁以下儿童进行免疫接种没有科学上的正当理由
I don't think there's any scientific justification for immunizing children under 12.
现在 至少这是有争议的 我不是领域专家 虽然我是一个不错的科学家 我知道如何阅读研究材料
Now, at least it's debatable and I'm not a domain expert, although I'm a decent scientist and I know how to read the research material.
And so, well, we'll see what we have to learn from these tectonic shifts underneath.
那么 嗯 我们将看到我们必须从这些结构性变化中学到什么
你可能会问自己 那到底是因为COVID病毒真的非常危险 导致了一次极端物理需求下的结构性变动
And you might ask yourself, well, was that a tectonic shift in dire physical necessity because the COVID virus was genuinely so dangerous or was it an indication tectonically of our absolute inadequacy in the face of even a moderate existential challenge?
还是这表明了我们在面对即使是中等程度的生存挑战时的绝对不足？
也许是一点点A列和一点点B列
And maybe it's a little column A in a little column B, you know, so.
你知道的 所以
I have to ask the question,
我不得不问这个问题
if we were to make Jordan Peterson the president of the world, and these were your decisions to make,
如果我们让乔丹·彼得森成为世界总统 这些决定由你来做
你知道你会采取什么不同的做法 或者如何应对这种病毒在WH出现的情况？
do you know what you would have done differently, or in response to this virus emerging in Wuhan?
I would say, well, thank you for the offer, but I declined the position,
我会说 感谢你的提议 但我拒绝这个职位
and the reason I would say that is because I think the right solution to the most serious problems is to be found at the level of the individual.
我之所以这么说 是因为我认为对最严重问题的正确解决方案应该在个人层面找到
So I don't think if I wanted to pursue what I regarded as the ultimate goal,
所以我不认为如果我想追求我认为的终极目标
the ultimate goal for me is the encouragement of the individual.
对我来说 终极目标是对个人的激励
And that's not essentially a political enterprise.
这本质上不是一个政治事业
It's essentially a theological enterprise.
这本质上是一个神学事业
And politics has to be subordinate to that.
政治必须服从于此
所以我在整个人生过程中一直在思考 是否会选择政治职业
And so I've debated throughout the entire course of my life whether I would adopt a political career.
这是我很年轻时的初衷 我会说大约14岁
was my initial ambition when I was very young 14 I would say
but when push came to shove at every decision point in my life if I had to choose between working on the encouragement of the individual and pursuing a or pursuing a political career
但是 当我生命中的每个决策点 面临紧要关头时 如果我必须在激励个体还是追求政治生涯之间做出选择
I always chose the the former and that's happened every time the decision has come up
我总是选择前者 每当这个决定出现时都是这样
I've been approached by people in Canada to involve myself more deeply in a practical role and also publicly as a political figure
加拿大的一些人接触过我 希望我更深入地参与现实角色 作为一个公众政治人物 但我更愿意做我现在的事
but I'd rather do what I'm doing I'm in contact with people working politically all the time both on the people in the middle people on the right people on the left
我一直与政治工作的人保持联系 包括中间派、右派和左派的人
I'm agnostic about that because I know full well that conservatives have something to say and left-leaning liberals have something to say that's basically predicated to some degree on their temperament
我对此持不置可否的态度 因为我很清楚保守派和左倾的自由派都有话要说
so conservatives tend to be more conscientious so that's orderly and industrious dutiful patriotic willing to make and keep verbal contracts reliable capable of implementation at the level of detail
这在某种程度上基于他们的性格 保守派倾向于更有责任心 也就是有序和勤奋、尽职、爱国、愿意制定并遵守口头合约、可靠 能够在细节层面上执行。
that's kind of conservative virtues there but they tend to be lower in creativity openness to experience they don't think is divergent Lee
这些是保守派的美德 但他们往往在创造力、对经验的开放性方面较低
他们的思维不那么发散 他们的责任心往往限制了他们的创造力,而自由派类型 他们在对经验的开放性方面得分高
and their conscientiousness tends to constrain their creativity whereas the liberal types they're high in openness to experience that's the creativity dimension
这是创造力维度 但他们在责任心方面 特别是有序性方面 得分较低
but they tend to be lower in conscientiousness particularly orderliness and so what that means is
这意味着 具有自由派性格的人倾向于成为创意人/企业家 而具有保守性格的人倾向于成为管理和行政人员
those with a liberal temperament tend to be creative slash entrepreneurs and those with a conservative temperament tend to be managerial and administrative
这并不意味着他们不能经营企业
that doesn't mean they can't run businesses well you want a conservative person to run your business
嗯 你可能希望一个保守的人来经营你的企业 你可能想要一个更自由派的人给你提供一些天马行空的想法
you might want a more liberal person to pepper you with off-the-wall ideas you know and then if you're gonna run an enterprise
然后 如果你要运营一个企业、商业或社会 就必须有不同性格的人之间的持续对话 这样我们才能保持国家船只 比方说
business or a society there has to be a continual dialogue between people of different temperaments so that we can keep the ship of state let's say
朝着一个不断变化的目的地前进 这就是为什么自由言论如此必要
tracking to an ever-moving destination that's why free speech is so necessary
it's not another right it's the right so because none of us know what's going
这不仅仅是另一个权利 它是权利之本 因为我们谁也不知道归根结底会发生什么 因为未来确实与过去不同
on in the final analysis because the future is different than the past really
we have to talk about what to do all the time because even if we made wise decisions in the past that doesn't mean that we can mindlessly replicate those
我们必须一直讨论该做什么 因为即使我们过去做出了明智的决定 这并不意味着我们现在可以不假思索地复制这些决定 来应对变化的未来
decisions right now in the present to deal with a changing future
所以我想帮助鼓励人们成为能够参与自由对话的人
so I want to help encourage people to become the sort of people who can engage in that free dialogue
我认为这是向前迈进的最好方式 特别是当我们所有人都变得更加技术强大时
and I think that's the best way forward especially as we all become more technologically powerful
it's like you better be smart enough to use your iPhone and that's pretty damn smart let's say wise because that's no trivial gadget
就像 你最好足够聪明地使用你的iPhone 那是相当聪明的 可以说是明智的 因为那不是一个微不足道的小玩意儿
and if you're not careful with it it will turn on you we'll build
如果你不小心 它就会攻击你 例如 我们会在我们的人工智能系统中构建专制的假设 然后看看情况会怎样 所以如果你要拥有一颗氢弹 你最好足够明智地使用它
authoritarian presumptions into our artificial intelligence systems for example and then look the hell out so if you're gonna have a hydrogen bomb you
在激励个体这一点上 我们生命中都有我们想要鼓励的人 我们希望如此
better be wise enough to wield it on that point of the encouragement of the individual we all have people in our lives that we want to encourage we hope
是的 我们希望 对吧？我们有时会试图强加我们自己的偏见、我们自己对他们的意图
yeah we hope right and we sometimes fall foul of trying to force our own bias our own intention for them on them what is the best way if I've got a friend in my or a partner that I want to encourage
如果我生命中有一个朋友或伴侣 我想鼓励他们从绝望的地方走向更好的地方
to come out of their place of despair into a better place,
我该如何有效地做到这一点 而不是压倒他们或扼杀他们 或让他们感到不足
how do I effectively do that without overpowering them or stifling them or making them feel inadequate,
这有时是试图改变所爱之人的后果
which is sometimes the consequence of trying to change someone you love?
好吧 以身作则是个好方法
Well, example's good,
但我想说的是 不要再误以为你知道什么对这个人来说是最好的
but then I would say disabuse yourself of the notion that you know what is best for this person.
你不知道 不仅你不知道 你实际上不想承担那种责任 有两个原因
You don't, not only do you not know, you actually don't want that responsibility for two reasons.
比如说 他们按照你的说法行事 对他们有好处
Let's say they do what you say and something good happens to them.
那么 这是谁的胜利？
Well, whose victory is that?
是你的还是他们的？
Yours or theirs?
如果是你的 你是不是刚好偷走了它？
And if it's yours, did you just steal it?
然后假设他们按照你的建议 失败了
And then let's say they fail following your advice.
好吧 他们为此付出了代价
Well, they pay the price for that.
你可以愉快地跳开说 嗯 我应该说得更谨慎一些
And you can skip away merrily and say, well, I should have spoke more carefully.
就像 你不要干涉人们的命运
It's like, you don't mess about with people's destiny.
你不知道他们要去哪里
You do not know where they're headed.
Now, having said that,
既然如此 你就继续做这个采访中你正在做的事 在这个播客中
you do what you're doing in this interview, in this podcast.
你问人们问题 真正的问题 你知道吗？
You ask people questions, real questions, you know?
比如 你感觉怎么样？
Like, how are you feeling?
哦 我今天感觉不太好
Oh, I'm not doing so good today.
那 怎么了？
Well, you know, what's up?
发生了什么事？
What's going on?
你不能想 好吧 我要问问题来引导这个人往特定的方向发展 因为那是同样的游戏 同样的工具性游戏
And you can't think, well, I'm gonna ask questions to lead this person in a particular direction, because that's the same game, the same instrumental game.
你必须看看你想知道什么
You have to see what it is that you want to know.
Because I see this when people ask me questions after my lectures, you know, now and then,
因为 看 当人们在我的讲座后问我问题 你知道 偶尔 或者在问答环节 偶尔人们会起来提一个真正的问题
or during a Q&A, now and then people get up and they'll ask a real question.
它是持续对话的一部分
It's part of the ongoing dialogue.
某些事情触动了他们
Something struck them.
他们站起来
They stand up.
他们真的想知道某件事
There's something they really want to know.
这是一个诚实的问题
It's an honest question.
And that goes real well, but not infrequently.
而这很好 但不时地 有人站起来 带着一个小小的准备好的讲话 将其包装成一个问题
someone stands up with a little prepared speech that's packaged as a question.
这些人中很多都是基督教传统主义者
So I get this from Christian traditionalists fairly frequently.
他们站起来问我关于我的宗教信仰 但实际上他们想做的是逼我承认 我应该接受耶稣基督作为我的救世主
They get up and they ask me about my religious convictions, but really what they wanna do is corner me into admitting that I should accept Jesus Christ as my savior and join a particular,
并加入一个特定的 比如说 教派
let's say, denomination.
这不是一个问题
It's not a question.
这只是一种操纵
It's just a manipulation.
所以你的问题 像你的陈述一样 你的问题应该是诚实的
And so your questions, like your statements, your question should be honest.
如果你问人们问题并且真的倾听 他们会自己解开纠结
And if you ask people questions and you really listen, they will untangle themselves.
这也是部分原因 为什么人们喜欢被关注 你知道 像
And that's partly why people love to be attended to.
如果我在街上遇到人 你知道 我会问他们的名字
You know, like if I meet people on the street, you know, I ask them their name,
当他们走近我时 他们通常都很慌乱 他们并不是真的想打扰我 所有他们就很慌张
they're all usually flustered when they come up to me, they don't really want to interrupt me and then they're flustered.
我做的第一件事就是握他们的手 问他们的名字
And the first thing I do is shake their hand and ask them their name.
我记不太住名字 但我会听 他们知道如何说出自己的名字
And I listen, I'm not that good at remembering names, but I listen to it. and they know how to say their name.
所以这会让他们平静下来 然后它某种程度上将他们作为一个人从背景中标记出来 是吧？（译注：在某种程度上将他们作为一个独特的个体与背景区分开来 这种互动帮助人们感到被重视和被认可 而不只是在人群中混为一谈）
And so it kind of settles them down and then it sort of marks them out as a person against the background, eh?
然后如果我关注他们 倾听 他们会在大概10秒内告诉我我需要知道的东西
And then if I pay attention to them and listen, they will tell me something in like 10 seconds that I need to know.
因为他们有话要说
Because they have something to say, you know?
然后 如果你倾听 人们会告诉你他们要说什么 然后你就会变得明智 因为你收集了所有这些
And then if you listen, people tell you what they have to say and then you get wise because you collect all that.
所以你想帮助某人
And so you want to help someone.
首先 你会决定你的目标是帮助 对吧？
Well, first of all, you would decide that you're aiming towards help, right?
而你以无知的精神去做这件事
And that you do that in the spirit of ignorance.
每个优秀的临床医生都会学到的就是 我不知道你要去哪里
This is what every good clinician learns is I don't know where you're headed.
我不知道你哪里不对劲
I don't know what's wrong with you.
这是个难题 伙计
This is a hard problem, man.
就像 你的问题是什么？
It's like, what's your problem?
我不知道你的问题是什么
I don't know what your problem is.
所以我们首先找出这个 然后我们找出一个你可以问人们的问题
So let's find that out first and then let's find out one thing you can ask people.
This is actually useful in an argument with someone you love.
这实际上在与你爱的人争论时很有用 他们对你不满
They're upset with you.
你对满意的前提条件是什么？
What are your preconditions for satisfaction?
现在 我不会这样表达
Now, I wouldn't state it like that.
就像 如果我现在能在这场争论的背景下给你想要的东西 并且我不是以一种操纵的方式这样做
It's like, if I could give you what you wanted right now in the context of this argument, and I wasn't doing it in a manipulative way,
我需要说什么或做什么才能原则上让你满意？
what is it that I would have to say or do that would in principle satisfy you?
这是个难题 你知道的
And that's a hard question, you know?
那人可能会说 嗯 我认为你应该为这个道歉 然后我会说 我应该用什么话来说？
And the person might say, well, I think you should apologize about this, and then I will say, what words should I use?
他们会说 嗯 如果你爱我 你就会知道
And they'll say, well, if you loved me, you'd know.
我会说 不 我愚蠢又无知
And I would say, no, I'm stupid and ignorant and I don't know what the right words are to satisfy you.
我不知道用什么正确的话来满足你 那你为什么不帮帮我 我会笨拙而不优雅地说出来 以一种真诚的行动表达我的和平承诺
So why don't you give me a hand with that and I'll utter them in elegantly and awkwardly in a good faith demonstration of my commitment to peace.
这可能不够好 因为如果是我自己想出来的话可能会更好 但也许下次我可以做得稍微好一点
And that won't be so good because maybe it would have been better if I came up with it myself, but maybe next time I can do slightly better.
这是有效的 这要求追问你的人仔细思考
And that works, it requires the person who's after you to think through the question even of
甚至是否有任何可以说出或做出的事情能使他们满意
whether there's anything that could be said or done that would satisfy them.
And if the answer to that is no,
如果答案是否定的 那么 这段关系可能就结束了
well, probably the relationship is over.
但肯定的是 被他们指责的那个人被置于了一个绝对不可能的位置
But certainly the person that they're accusing has been put in an absolutely impossible position.
但通常 几乎不可避免地 如果那个人稍微沉思一下
But usually, almost inevitably, if the person meditates on it for a bit,
确实有一些事情可以让他们满意 可以通过谈判解决 只要他们愿意给你机会去做 你知道 愚蠢而糟糕地去做
there is something that would satisfy them that can be negotiated as long as they're willing to give you the opportunity to do it stupidly and badly.
所以 倾听 伙计
So, listening, man.
我两周前和吉米·卡尔谈过 那位著名的喜剧演员 是的 那次谈话真的很有趣
Jimmy Carr, I talked to Jimmy Carr two weeks ago, the famous comedian, yeah, it was real interesting.
他说喜剧是娱乐领域中最对话式的
He said comedy is the most dialogical of the entertainment forums.
And I thought, well, what do you mean by that?
我当时想 你这么说是什么意思 因为你只是在说 这是一段独白 对吧？
Because you're just, it's a monologue, right?
现在我做独白 但我会注意观众
Now I do monologues, but I pay attention to the audience.
我总是和观众中的个别人交谈 观察他们的反应 听整个观众的反应
I'm always talking to individual people in the audience and watching their reactions and listening to the audience as a whole.
所以即使这是一场讲座 比方说 或者是一次谈话
So even though it's a lecture, let's say, or a talk,
I'm watching the audience and responding.
我观察着观众并作出回应 所以我们处于一种舞蹈中
So we're in a kind of dance.
卡尔指出 喜剧演员在他们上路之前 这几乎总是这样 他们有他们的新节目
Well, Carr pointed out that comedians, before they hit the road, and this is virtually invariably the case, they have their new routines.
So they're corpus of potentially funny jokes.
他们有可能有趣的笑话的语料库 然后他们做了200场演出
And then they do 200 shows in front of small audiences.
在小型观众面前 观众要么笑要么不笑 如果你在听 你就会收集所有让人们笑的笑话
And the audience either laughs or doesn't.
And if you're listening, you collect all the jokes that people laugh at.
如果你倾听 你会收集到所有引发观众为之而笑的笑话 如果你这样做了200次 你就会拥有你所听到的全部的笑话 但你需要倾听
If you do that 200 times, you have nothing but hilarious material, but you listened.
然后你就可以出门上路了
And then you can go out on the road.
这对我来说非常有趣 因为幽默是一个在体验上和概念上都很神秘的现象
and that was very interesting to me because humor is a mysterious phenomenon
它在某种程度上是先于认知和本能的 但它也极其复杂 然后它还有一种超越性 对吧
experientially and conceptually and it's sort of precognitive and instinctual but it's also extremely sophisticated then there's an element of transcendence about it, right?
因为你可以嘲笑自己 而那在某种意义上是最高形式的幽默
Because you can laugh at yourself and that's in some sense the highest form of humor.
所以很有趣的是我们可以在批评和提升自己的同时发现这是极其愉快的
And so it's so interesting that we can criticize and elevate ourselves at the same time and that we find that intensely pleasurable.
所以一个好的喜剧演员通过这种方式进行收集 与观众分享 他在听
And so a good comedian collects ways to do that, shares them with the audience and he's listening.
所以如果你想帮助某人 帮助某人的最佳方式不是给他们建议 而是倾听他们
And so if you want to help someone, the best way to help someone is not to give them advice, but to listen to them, so.
我实际上在吉米·卡尔之前有位客人来参加了这个播客
I had a guest actually come on this podcast before Jimmy Carr.
吉米·卡尔两周前上节目 我们进行了一场关于幸福及其本质的精彩对话
Jimmy Carr was on two weeks ago and we had a great conversation about happiness and the nature of happiness.
而吉米·卡尔之前的那位客人在我的日记本上写下了一个问题 这是我们现在有的一个传统 所有来上节目的客人都会为下一位客人写一个问题
And the guest before Jimmy Carr wrote in my diary, which is a tradition we have now where all the guests that come on write a question for the next guest.
所以这里有一个问题是给你的
So there is a question there for you.
但那位客人写下了一个改变了他生活的问题 那就是 你幸福吗？
But the guest wrote a question which changed his life, which is, are you happy?
通过阅读你的作品并理解你对幸福的立场 以及幸福不是追求目标这一点 这真的打动了我
And I, from reading your work and understanding your position on happiness and it not being the thing to aim for, which really struck me because I thought, you know,
因为我曾以为 生活的北极星是试着去寻求幸福
I thought life was the North Star of our lives was to try and be happy.
我想我的问题是我本来想问你那个问题
I guess my question is, what, I was gonna ask you that question.
追求做一个好人 并为幸福祈祷
Aim to be good and pray for happiness.
所以我想问的问题基本上是 如果我关心你的话 我问你什么问题更好？
So the question I was gonna, it was pretty much that, is what is a better question for me to ask you if I'm checking in on you,
因为我们出于好意提出那个问题
because we asked that question with good intentions.
你幸福吗？
Are you happy?
那么 有什么更好的问题可以问乔丹·彼得森
What's a better question for me to ask Jordan Peterson?
你过得怎么样？
How are you doing?
灿烂且糟糕
Brilliantly and terribly.
这就像 你知道 当你听一首深刻的音乐作品时 一首涵盖整个情感体验的作品 它不是快乐的
That's, you know, when you listen to a profound piece of music, one that sort of spans the whole emotional experience, it's not happy.
快乐是电梯音乐（译注：电梯音乐 通常指那种在商业场所如购物中心、酒店、电梯等背景播放的轻柔、中性、不具侵扰性的音乐 电梯音乐通常节奏平缓、旋律简单 不包含太多情感表达 因而有时被用来形容那些过于平淡、缺乏特色的音乐作品 ）
Happy is elevator music.
但可能你根本就不应该听那种音乐
And probably you just shouldn't listen to that at all.
对吧 你想 为什么？
Right, and you think, why?
嗯 它无害 它轻薄 它甜蜜
Well, it's harmless, it's treetally, it's sweet.
简单 缺乏深度 它浅薄 这是个问题
Simple, it lacks depth, it's shallow, that's a problem.
它没有那种深沉的敬畏和恐怖感
It doesn't have that deep sense of awe and horror,
我会说 这是所有最佳音乐的特征
I would say, that is characteristic of the best of all music.
你知道 你听一些简单的音乐 所谓的
You know, you listen to some simple music, so-called.
汉克·威廉姆斯就是一个很好的例子
Hank Williams is a good example.
你知道 那位五十年代的布鲁斯牛仔 他27岁因酗酒去世 他的声音听起来像一个80岁的老人
You know, the blues cowboy from the fifties who died of alcoholism when he was 27 and whose voice sounds like an 80 year old man.
旋律很简单 但是歌曲和声音一点也不简单
Simple melody, you know, but there's nothing simple in the song and in the voice.
它深刻 就像布鲁斯
It's deep, you know, it's like the blues.
就像二十年代美国的黑人布鲁斯
It's like black blues in the States from the twenties.
这显然是受到那个传统的影响
And this was certainly influenced by that tradition.
这是对深刻苦难的承认 同时你感受到音乐的美妙超越
There's this admission of a deep suffering at the same time as you get the beautiful transcendence of the music.
这意味着 你知道 从最根本的意义上来说 这很可怕 但是你需要一种痛苦的解药
And that's meaning, you know, that's awful in the most fundamental sense, but you need an antidote to suffering and it has to be deep.
它必须是深刻的 深刻地感动你的构造 这不是一件微不足道的事情
And deep moves you tectonically, and it's not a trivial thing.
但那比幸福更好
But that's better than happiness.
也许如果你幸运 在你追求它和沉浸其中时 你会感到快乐 当这发生时你应该跪下来感激
And maybe if you're lucky, while you're pursuing that, and while you're immersed in it, you get to be happy, and you should fall on your knees and be grateful for that when it happens.
你知道 这是一份礼物
You know, it's a gift.
It really is a gift.
这真的是一份礼物 它出乎意料地降临于你 那就是你的幸福
And it comes upon you unexpectedly, your happiness, you know?
但是你的目标是攀登至你能想象到的最高峰
But you aim to climb uphill to the highest peak you can possibly envision.
这比幸福更重要
And that's better than happiness.
你为什么要包括“糟糕”这个词呢？
Why did you include terribly?
Well, for example, now, when I go,
比如现在 当我去世界上任何地方 人们走近我 我不会说他们见到我很高兴 他们经常是含泪的
wherever I go in the world, people come up to me and they're usually, I wouldn't say they're happy to see me.
They're often in tears, you know?
并且他们经常会讲述一个相当艰难的故事
And they often have a pretty rough story to relate.
他们可能曾经想过自杀、虚无主义或者有杀人的念头 或者束缚、绝望 他们很快就会告诉我这一切
You know, they were suicidal or nihilistic or homicidal are trapped, desperate, you know, and they tell me that real fast.
然后他们说 我在很大程度上克服了这些 感谢你的帮助
And then they say, I've overcome that to a large degree and thank you for that.
你会想 这样的事情一次又一次地发生真是太了不起了
And you think, well, that's really something to have that happen over and over.
In some ways you might think, well, how could anything better possibly happen to you
在某些方面 你可能会想 还有什么比全世界的陌生人这样走近你 如此快速地像老朋友一样敞开心扉而更好的事情呢？但同时这也是一件可怕的事情
than to have people come up to you all over the world, strangers, and open themselves up like that, like they're old friends so quickly.
因为即使在他们胜利的启示中 你也能看到他们最初的绝望的深度
But at the same time, it's an awful thing because you see, even in the revelation of their triumph, the initial depth of their despair.
So I wouldn't change that, but it's not nothing.
所以我无法改变这一点 但这并非无关紧要 它当然不仅仅是幸福 它比幸福更好 但它几乎难以承担
It's certainly not just happiness.
It's better than happiness, but it's almost unbearable.
再次泪流
God, tears again.
在英国的这两周真是难以置信
It's been quite two weeks in the UK.
这真是太棒了
It's been amazing.
这个国家真是太伟大了
Such a great country, this country.
这是一个如此深刻的地方
Such a profound place.
能够见到剑桥和牛津 被学生们欢迎 真是太美妙了
And it was so wonderful to see Cambridge and Oxford and to be welcomed by the students.
我看到围绕街区的长队和你得到的反应
I saw the cues around the block and the reaction you got.
我在剑桥看了你的演讲 能看到这一点真是太好了 因为我知道 你做你所做的事并非为了获得认可
I watched the talk in Cambridge and it was so wonderful to see because I know that you don't do what you do for credit.
那完全相反于 追求你的真理 并以真理为目标
That kind of seems to be the antithesis of pursuing your truth and doing it in the cause of truth.
但看到一个我知道对这么多人产生了如此深远影响的人以这种方式被接纳 真是太美妙了
But it was so wonderful to see someone that I know has had such a profound impact on so many be received in such a way.
我们有一个结束传统
We have a closing tradition.
我不想这样做 但我们国家一位真正伟大的年轻CEO 昨天坐在这里 他创办了一家价值数十亿美元的公司 真是个了不起的家伙
One of the, you know, I don't want to do this, but one of the really great CEOs in our country, a young guy who's bought a multi-billion dollar company, really great guy, sat here yesterday.
实际上我第一次告诉他他为谁写下了问题
And I actually told him for the first time who he was writing the question for.
我简直不敢相信他的表情
And I couldn't believe his face.
哦 我的天 那是我最想共进晚餐的人
Oh my God, that's the one person I want to have dinner with.
这可能是我们国家最成功的年轻人
This is probably the most successful young person in our country.
他是 所以他知道他在为谁写这个问题
And so he knew who he was writing the question for.
所以前一位嘉宾为你写下的问题是 你为什么做你所做的？
So the question that the previous guest wrote for you is, why do you do what you do?
看看会发生什么
To see what will happen.
有些程序你无法预测 对吧？
Some programs you cannot predict, right?
你无法预测它们将如何结束
You cannot predict how they're going to end.
你必须践行它们
You have to run them.
我相信真理会拯救世界
Well, you know, I believe that truth will save the world.
我相信这一点
I believe that.
So you speak truthfully.
所以你诚实地说话 然后看看会发生什么 你承担你的后果
And you watch what happens, and you take your consequences.
也许你希望并相信 归根结底
You know, and maybe you hope and have some faith that in the final analysis,
事情会朝着对你有利的方向发展 但也许会 也许不会 但这就是信念 不是吗？
things will work out in your favor, but perhaps they will and perhaps they won't.
But that's faith, eh?
那就是信仰 那就是信仰
That's faith.
信仰并不是相信你认为荒谬的事情 牺牲你的才智
Faith isn't believing in things you regard as ridiculous, sacrificing your intellect.
它是一个决定
It's a decision, you know?
真理、美丽和爱会拯救世界吗？
Oh, will truth, beauty, and love save the world?
嗯 你可以找出答案
Well, you can find out.
仅仅说谢谢似乎不足以感谢你对我的影响 以及刚才这段时间你所给予我的东西
Thank you doesn't seem to quite cut it for the impact you've had even on me and also for giving me your time.
我知道你深知时间的巨大价值
I know you understand the tremendous value of time.
我在你的工作中深深地看到这一点
I've seen it so much in your work.
所以我要说谢谢 但我还要做出一个我认为更重要的承诺 那就是保持真实
So I'm going to say thank you, but I'm also going to make a commitment to do something which I think is more important, which is just to be truthful.
我认为凭借我所拥有的平台和我未来的岁月 也许这是我能为世界做的最大的好事
And I think with the platform I have in the years I have ahead of me, maybe that's the greatest good that I can do to the world.
所以因为你来到这里 这是我想对你做出的承诺和誓言 作为我能以因果报应的方式给予的最高形式的感谢
So because you've come here, that's a pledge and a commitment I want to make you as my highest form of thanks that I can give in a karmic way.
希望那将使世成为一个对所有人来说都更美好的地方
Hopefully that will make the world a better place for everybody.
至少 它会帮助确保你不会让世界变得更糟
Well at least it will help ensure that you won't make the world worse place.
非常感谢你
Thank you so much.